A Guide to the Virginia Commission on Constitutional Revision Records, 1968-1969
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Virginia Commission on Constitutional Revision Records 1968-1969
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms72-002
4 containers; 2.0 cu. ft.
Records of the Virginia Commission on Constitutional Revision, including articles of the constitution, minutes and summaries of actions, reports of subcommittees, correspondence and memoranda, commentary, drafts, and galley proofs of revised constitution.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Virginia Commission on Constitutional Revision Records were donated to Newman Library in 1969 with the proviso that they not be released to the public before January 1, 1971. They were received in Special Collections in 1972.
Historical Information
Virginia's first constitution was adopted in 1776. The constitution was revised in 1830, 1851, 1864, 1870 and 1902. The need for another revision was mandated to conform with new federal laws concerning civil rights and to loosen regulations on state-issued bonds and borrowing. A 1968 joint resolution by the Virginia General Assembly approved a commission to revise the constitution, and Governor Mills E. Godwin Jr. appointed the commission later that year. The commission proceeded to study the constitution for the rest of the year before undertaking the task of revising the constitution in 1969. The articles involved in this process were: Bill of Rights, Franchise, Division of Powers, Legislative, Executive, Judiciary, Local Government, Education, Corporations, Taxation and Finance, Conservation, and Future Changes. The original constitution greatly influenced the current version, and numerous parts remained unaltered in the revision. Approved by referendum, Completed in 1969 at Williamsburg, the revised constitution came into effect on July 1, 1971 and continues to be in use for the commonwealth of Virginia. Undertaking the task of revising a constitution usually occurs no more than once a generation, which made the revision a significant occasion for the commonwealth of Virginia.
Scope and Content
This collection contains papers associated with the 1971 revision of the Virginia Constitution. The commission revised the following articles in the constitution in 1969: Bill of Rights, Franchise, Division of Powers, Legislative, Executive, Judiciary, Local Government, Education, Corporations, Taxation and Finance, Conservation, and Future Changes. The collection contains materials associated with these articles as well as commission minutes and summaries of meetings, correspondence and memoranda, galley proofs, and drafts of the constitution. The majority of these materials have comments from the commission to other members about changes that needed to be made. The notes also include questions that needed to be addressed about the constitution and recommendations to better it. The principle documents are commentaries on the articles articles and reports of the various commission subcommittees.
Arrangement
The collection retains its original order, within the following categories: Final Revision, Minutes and Summaries of Action, Correspondence and Memoranda, Subcommittee Reports, and Commentary for Draft Constitution.
Contents List
- Final Revision 1968 (Box-folder 1-1)
- Minutes and Summaries of Action 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1-2)
- Correspondence and Memoranda 1968 (Box-folder 1-3)
- Subcommittee Reports 1968
  - Bill of Rights Subcommittee, [2 folders] (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Legislative and Judicial Subcommittee, [2 folders] (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Local Government Subcommittee, [2 folders] (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Executive and State Administration Subcommittee, [3 folders] (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Taxation and Finance Subcommittee, [2 folders] (Box-folder 2-3)
- Preliminary Draft Constitution 1968, [2 folders] (Box-folder 3-1)
- Galley Proofs n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 3-2)
- Commentary for Draft Constitution 1968, n.d.
  - Introductory Commentary (Box-folder 3-3)
  - Bill of Rights (Box-folder 3-4)
  - Franchise (Box-folder 3-5)
  - Division of Power (Box-folder 3-6)
  - Legislative (Box-folder 3-7)
  - Executive (Box-folder 4-1)
  - Judiciary (Box-folder 4-2)
  - Local Government (Box-folder 4-3)
  - Education (Box-folder 4-4)
  - Corporations (Box-folder 4-5)
  - Taxation (Box-folder 4-6)
  - Conservation (Box-folder 4-7)
  - Future Changes (Box-folder 4-8)